<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE chapter PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../../Reference_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<section id="sect-Reference_Guide-APIs-Organization_API">
	<title>Organization API</title>
	<para>
		The
		<literal>exo.platform.services.organization</literal>
		package has five main components: user, user profile, group,
		membership type and membership.
		There is an additional component that serves as an entry point into
		Organization API -
		<literal>OrganizationService</literal>
		component,
		that provides handling functionality for the five components.
	</para>
	<para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject role="html">
				<imagedata fileref="images/AuthenticationAndIdentity/OrganizationServiceClassDiagram.png" format="PNG" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
			<imageobject role="fo">
				<imagedata fileref="images/AuthenticationAndIdentity/OrganizationServiceClassDiagram.png" scalefit="1" format="PNG" align="center"/>
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</para>
	<para>
		The
		<literal>User</literal>
		component contains basic information about a user - such as
		username, password, first name, last name, and email. The
		<literal>User Profile</literal>
		component contains extra information about a user, such as user's
		personal information, and business information.
		You can also add additional information about a user if your application
		requires it.
		The
		<literal>Group</literal>
		component contains a group graph. The
		<literal>Membership Type</literal>
		component
		contains a list of predefined membership types.
		Finally, the
		<literal>Membership</literal>
		component connects a User, a Group and a Membership Type.
	</para>
	<para>
		A user can have one or more memberships within a group, for example:
		user A can have the 'member' and 'admin' memberships in group /user.
		A user belongs to a group if he has at least one membership in that
		group.
      </para>
	<para>
		Exposing the Organization API to developers the OrganizationService component
		provides developers with access
		to handler objects for managing each of the five components -
		UserHandler, UserProfileHandler, GroupHandler, MembershipTypeHandler,
		and MembershipHandler.
      </para>
	<para>
		The five central API components are really designed like persistent
		entities, and handlers are really specified like data access objects
		(DAO).
      </para>
	<para>
		Organization API simply describes a contract, meaning it is not a concrete
		implementation. The described components are interfaces,
		allowing for different concrete implementations. In practial terms that means,
		you can replace the existing implementation with a different one.
	</para>
</section>

