<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN"
"http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../../Reference_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Skinning_Portal">
  <title>Skinning the portal</title>

  <section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Overview">
    <title>Overview</title>
    <para>&PRODUCT;
      provides robust skinning support for the entire portal User
      Interface (UI). This includes support for skinning all of the
      common portal elements as well as being able to provide custom
      skins and window decoration for individual portlets. All of this
      designed with common graphic resource reuse and ease of development
      in mind.
    </para>
  </section>

  <section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Types_of_Styles">
    <title>Skin Components</title>

    <para>
      The complete skinning of a page can be decomposed into three main
      parts:
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Portal Skin</term>
        <listitem>

          <para>
            The portal skin contains the css styles for the portal and its various UI
            components. This should include all the UI components except for the window
            decorators and portlet specific styles.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Window Styles</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The CSS styles associated with the porlet window decorators. The window
            decorators contain the control buttons and boarders surrounding each portlet.
            Individual portlets can have their own window decorator selected, or be 
            rendered without one.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>

      <varlistentry>
        <term>Portlet Skins</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The portlet skins effect how portlets are rendered on the page. There are two
            main ways this can be affected:
          </para>
          <variablelist>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Portlet Specification CSS Classes</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>The
                  portlet specification defines a set of css classes that should
                  be available to portlets. &PRODUCT; provides
                  these classes as part of the portal skin. This allows each portal skin to
                  define its own look and feel for these default values.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>
            <varlistentry>
              <term>Portlet Skins</term>
              <listitem>
                <para>&PRODUCT;
                  provides a means for portlet css files to be loaded based on
                  the current portal skin. This allows a portlet to provide different 
                  css styles to better match the current portal look and feel. Portlet skins
                  provide a much more customizable css experience than just using the portlet
                  specification css classes.
                </para>
              </listitem>
            </varlistentry>

          </variablelist>

        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <note>
      <para>
        The window decorators and the default portlet specification css classes should
        be considered separate types of skinning components, but they need to be included
        as part of the overall portal skin. The portal skin must include these component´s 
        css classes or they will not be displayed correctly.</para>
      <para>
        A portlet skin doesn't need to be included as part of the portal skin and can
        be included within the portlets web application.
    </para>
    </note>
  </section>

  <section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Skin_Switching">
    <title>Skin Selection</title>

    <section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Skin_Switching-UI">
      <title>Skin Selection Through the User Interface</title>
      <para>
        There are a few means in which a skin can be selected to be displayed
        to the user. The easiest way to change the skin is select it through
        the user interface. An admin can change the default skin for the portal, or
        a logged in user can select which skin they would prefer to be displayed.
	</para>
      <para>
        Please see the User Guide for information on how to change the skin using the user
        interface.
	</para>

    </section>
    <section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Skin_Switching-config">
      <title>Setting the Default Skin within the Configuration Files</title>
      <para>
        The default skin can also be configured through the portal
        configuration files if using the admin user interface is not desired.
        This will allow for the portal to have the new default skin ready when &PRODUCT;
        is first started.
      </para>
      <para>
        The default skin of the portal is called
        <literal>Default</literal>. To change this value add a
        <literal>skin</literal> tag in the
        <literal>02portal.war/WEB-INF/conf/portal/portal/classic/portal.xml</literal>
        configuration file.
      </para>
      <para>
        To change the skin to
        <literal>MySkin</literal>
        you would make the following changes:
      </para>

      <programlisting role="XML">&lt;portal-config&gt;
                &lt;portal-name&gt;classic&lt;/portal-name&gt;
                &lt;locale&gt;en&lt;/locale&gt;
                &lt;access-permissions&gt;Everyone&lt;/access-permissions&gt;
                &lt;edit-permission&gt;*:/platform/administrators&lt;/edit-permission&gt;
                &lt;skin&gt;MySkin&lt;/skin&gt;
                ...
      </programlisting>
    </section>
  </section>

  <section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Skins_in_Page_Markups">
    <title>Skins in Page Markups</title>

    <para>A &PRODUCT;
      skin contains css styles for the portal's components but
      also shares components that may be reused in portlets. When &PRODUCT;
      generates a portal page markup, it inserts stylesheet links in the page's
      <literal>head</literal> tag.
    </para>

    <para>
      There are two main types of css links that will appear in the
      <literal>head</literal> tag: a link to the portal skin css file and a link 
      to the portlet skin css files.
    </para>

    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Portal Skin</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            The portal skin will appear as a single link to a css file. This
            link will contain contents from all the portal skin classes merged
            into one file. This allow for the portal skin to be transfered more
            quickly as a single file instead of many multiple smaller files.
            Included with every page render.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Portlet Skin</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
            Each portlet on a page may contribute its own style. The link to
            the portlet skin will only appear on the page if that portlet is
            loaded on the current page. A page may contain many portlet skin css
            links or none.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>

    <para>In the code fragment below you can see the two types of links:</para>

<programlisting role="XML">&lt;head&gt;
...
&lt;!-- The portal skin --&gt;
&lt;link id="CoreSkin" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href="/eXoResources/skin/Stylesheet.css" /&gt;

&lt;!-- The portlet skins --&gt;
&lt;link id="web_FooterPortlet" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href= "/web/skin/portal/webui/component/UIFooterPortlet/DefaultStylesheet.css" /&gt;
&lt;link id="web_NavigationPortlet" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href= "/web/skin/portal/webui/component/UINavigationPortlet/DefaultStylesheet.css" /&gt;
&lt;link id="web_HomePagePortlet" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href= "/portal/templates/skin/webui/component/UIHomePagePortlet/DefaultStylesheet.css" /&gt;
&lt;link id="web_BannerPortlet" rel="stylesheet" type="text/css" href= "/web/skin/portal/webui/component/UIBannerPortlet/DefaultStylesheet.css" /&gt;
...
&lt;/head&gt;
</programlisting>

  <note>
    <para>Window styles and the portlet specification CSS classes are included
      within the portal skin.</para>
  </note>
  </section>

  <section id="sect-Reference_Guid-Skin_Configuration-Skin_Service">
    <title>The Skin Service</title>
    <para>
    The skin service is a &PRODUCT; service which manages the various types of
    skins. It is reponsible for discovering and deploying the skins into the
    portal.
    </para>

    <section>
      <title>Skin configuration</title>

      <para>&PRODUCT; automatically discovers web archives that contain a
      file descriptor for skins (<filename>WEB-INF/gatein-resources.xml</filename>). This file is
      reponsible for specifying the portal, portlet and window decorators to be deployed into the
      skin service.
      </para>
      
      <para>The full schema can be found in lib directory:</para>
      <filename>exo.portal.component.portal.jar/gatein_resources_1_0.xsd</filename>
    
      <para>Here is an example where we define a skin (MySkin) with its CSS location, and specify a few window decorator skins: 
      </para>
      <programlisting role="XML">&lt;gatein-resources&gt;
  &lt;portal-skin&gt;
    &lt;skin-name&gt;MySkin&lt;/skin-name&gt;
    &lt;css-path&gt;/skin/myskin.css&lt;/css-path&gt;
    &lt;overwrite&gt;false&lt;/overwrite&gt;
  &lt;/portal-skin&gt;
&lt;/gatein-resources&gt;

  &lt;!-- window style --&gt;
  &lt;window-style&gt;
    &lt;style-name&gt;MyThemeCategory&lt;/style-name&gt;
    &lt;style-theme&gt;
      &lt;theme-name&gt;MyThemeBlue&lt;/theme-name&gt;
    &lt;/style-theme&gt;
    &lt;style-theme&gt;
      &lt;theme-name&gt;MyThemeRed&lt;/theme-name&gt;
    &lt;/style-theme&gt;
    ...
      </programlisting>
    </section>

  <section
    id="sect-Reference_Guide-How_to_Configure_a_Portal_Skin-SkinConfigListener">
    <title>Resource Request Filter</title>

    <para>Because of the Right-To-Left support all CSS files need to be
      retrieved through a Servlet filter and the web application needs to be
      configured to activate this filter. This is already done for
      01eXoResources.war web application which contains the default skin.</para>
    <para>
      Any new web applications containing skinning css files will
      need to have the following added to their
      <literal>web.xml</literal>
      :
    </para>

    <programlisting role="XML">&lt;filter&gt;
      &lt;filter-name&gt;ResourceRequestFilter&lt;/filter-name&gt;
      &lt;filter-class&gt;org.exoplatform.portal.application.ResourceRequestFilter&lt;/filter-class&gt;
      &lt;/filter&gt;

      &lt;filter-mapping&gt;
      &lt;filter-name&gt;ResourceRequestFilter&lt;/filter-name&gt;
      &lt;url-pattern&gt;*.css&lt;/url-pattern&gt;
      &lt;/filter-mapping&gt;</programlisting>
  </section>

    <note>
      <para>The <literal>display-name</literal> element will also need to
      be specified in the <literal>web.xml</literal> for the skinning service to work properly
      with the web application.</para>
    </note>
    
  </section>

  <section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Default_Skin">
    <title>The Default Skin</title>
    <para>
    The default skin for &PRODUCT; is located as part of the <literal>01eXoResource.war</literal>.
    The main files associated with the skin is show below:
    </para>
    
    <programlistingco>
      <areaspec>
        <area coords="1" id="area-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Default_Skin-gatein-resources" />
        <area coords="2" id="area-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Default_Skin-web" />
        <area coords="3" id="area-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Default_Skin-skin-Stylesheet" />
      </areaspec>
	<programlisting>WEB-INF/gatein-resources.xml
WEB-INF/web.xml
skin/Stylesheet.css</programlisting>
<calloutlist>
        <callout arearefs="area-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Default_Skin-gatein-resources">
          <para>gatein-resources.xml: defines the skin setup to use</para>
        </callout>
        <callout arearefs="area-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Default_Skin-web">
          <para>web.xml: contains the resource filer and has the display-name set</para>
        </callout>
        <callout arearefs="area-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Default_Skin-skin-Stylesheet">
          <para>Stylesheet.css: contains the CSS class definitions for this skin.</para>
        </callout>
      </calloutlist>
    </programlistingco>
    <variablelist>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>gatein-resources.xml</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
		    For the default portal skin, this file contains definitions for the portal skin, the window
		    decorations that this skin provides and well as defining some javascript resources which are not
		    related to the skin. The default portal skin doesn't directly define portlet skins, these should be
		    provided by the portlets themeselves.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>web.xml</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
	        For the default portal skin, the web.xml of the eXoResources.war will contains a lot
	        of information which is mostly irrelevant to the portal skining. The areas of interest
	        in this file is the resourcerequestfilter and the fact that the display-name is set.
          </para>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
      <varlistentry>
        <term>Stylesheet.css</term>
        <listitem>
          <para>
          The main portal skin stylesheet. The file is the main entry point to the css class definitions
          for the skin. Below is shown the contents of this file:
          </para>
          
    <programlistingco>
      <areaspec>
        <area coords="1" id="area-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Default_Skin-uiportletapplication" />
        <area coords="2" id="area-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Default_Skin-components" />
        <area coords="3" id="area-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Default_Skin-portletthemes" />
        <area coords="4" id="area-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Default_Skin-portlet" />
      </areaspec>
    <programlisting>@import url(DefaultSkin/portal/webui/component/UIPortalApplicationSkin.css);
@import url(DefaultSkin/webui/component/Stylesheet.css);
@import url(PortletThemes/Stylesheet.css);
@import url(Portlet/Stylesheet.css);</programlisting>
<calloutlist>
        <callout arearefs="area-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Default_Skin-uiportletapplication">
          <para>Skin for the main portal page.</para>
        </callout>
        <callout arearefs="area-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Default_Skin-components">
          <para>Skins for various portal components.</para>
        </callout>
        <callout arearefs="area-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Default_Skin-portletthemes">
          <para>Window decoration skins.</para>
        </callout>
        <callout arearefs="area-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Default_Skin-portlet">
          <para>The portlet specificiation css classes.</para>
        </callout>
      </calloutlist>
    </programlistingco>
		  <para>
		  Instead of defining all the CSS classes in this one file we are instead importing other css stylesheet files,
		  some of which may also import other CSS stylesheets. The css classes are split up between multiple files to make
		  it easier for new skins to reuse parts of the default skin.
		  </para>
		  <para>To reuse a CSS stylesheet from the default portal skin you would need to reference the default skin from eXoResources.
		  For example, to include the window decorators from the default skin within a new portal skin you would need to use this import: </para>
		  <programlisting>@import url(/eXoResources/skin/Portlet/Stylesheet.css);</programlisting>
		  <note>
		  <para>When the portal skin is added to the page, it merge all the css stylesheets into a single file.</para>
		  </note>
        </listitem>
      </varlistentry>
    </variablelist>
    
  
  </section>

  <section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-How_to_create_a_new_skin">
    <title>Creating New Skins</title>

    <section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-How_to_create_new_portal_skin">
      <title>Creating a New Portal Skin</title>
      
      <para>
        A new portal will need to be added to the portal through the skin service. As such the web application
        which contains the skin will need to be properly configured for the skin service to discover them. This 
        means properly configuring the ResourceRequestFilter and gatein-resources.xml.
      </para>

      <section>
        <title>Portal Skin Configuration</title>
        <para>
        The gatein-resources.xml will need to specify the new portal skin. This will include specifying the name
        of the new skin, where to locate its css stylesheet file and whether to overwrite an existing portal theme with
        the same name.
        </para>
        <programlisting role="XML">&lt;gatein-resources&gt;
  &lt;portal-skin&gt;
    &lt;skin-name&gt;MySkin&lt;/skin-name&gt;
    &lt;css-path&gt;/skin/myskin.css&lt;/css-path&gt;
    &lt;overwrite&gt;false&lt;/overwrite&gt;
  &lt;/portal-skin&gt;
&lt;/gatein-resources&gt;
      </programlisting>
      <para>The default portal skin and window styles are defined in
    <filename>01eXoResources.war/WEB-INF/gatein-resources.xml</filename>.
    </para>
      <note>
      <para>
      The css for the portal skin needs to contain the css for all the window decorations and the portlet specification
      css classes.
      </para>
      </note>
      </section>
    
      <section>
        <title>Portal Skin Preview Icon</title>
         <para>
         When selecting a skin it is possible to see a preview of what the skin will look like. The current skin needs to
         know about the skin icons for all the available skins, otherwise it will not be able
         to show the previews. When creating a new portal it is recommended to include the preview
         icons of the other skins and to update the other skins with your new portal skin preview.
         </para>

         <mediaobject>
		<imageobject>
			<imagedata fileref="images/PortalDevelopment/Skinning/portal-change-skin.png"
				format="PNG" width="444" />
		</imageobject>
	</mediaobject>

         <para>
         The portal skin preview icon is specified through the CSS of the portal skin. In order for the current portal skin
         to be able to display the preview it must specify a specific CSS class and set the icon as the background. 
         </para>
         <para>
         For a portal named <emphasis role="bold">MySkin</emphasis> in must define the following CSS class:
         </para>
         <programlisting>.UIChangeSkinForm .UIItemSelector .TemplateContainer .<emphasis
            role="bold">MySkinImage</emphasis></programlisting>
         

         <para>
         In order for the default skin to know about the skin icon for a new portal skin, the preview screenshot
         needs to be place in:</para>
         
         <filename>01eXoResources.war:/skin/DefaultSkin/portal/webui/component/customization/UIChangeSkinForm/background</filename>
         <para>
         The CSS stylesheet for the default portal needs to have the following updated with the preview icon css class. For a skin named 
         <emphasis
            role="bold">MySkin</emphasis> then the following needs to be updated:</para>
         <filename>01eXoResources.war:/skin/DefaultSkin/portal/webui/component/customization/UIChangeSkinForm/Stylesheet.css</filename>
         <programlisting>.UIChangeSkinForm .UIItemSelector .TemplateContainer .<emphasis
            role="bold">MySkinImage</emphasis> {
  margin: auto;
  width: 329px; height:204px;
  background: url('background/MySkin.jpg') no-repeat top;
  cursor: pointer ;
}</programlisting>

      </section>
    
    </section>

  <section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-How_to_create_new_themes">
    <title>Creating a New Window Style</title>

    <para>Window styles are the CSS applied to window decoration. When an
    administrator choose a new application to add on a page he can decide
    which style of decoration would go around the window if any.</para>

    <para><mediaobject>
        <imageobject>
          <imagedata fileref="images/PortalDevelopment/Skinning/windowStyles.png" format="PNG"
                     width="444" />
        </imageobject>
      </mediaobject></para>

	<section>
	<title>Window Style Configuration</title>
	<para>
	Window Styles are defined within a gatein-resources.xml file which is used by the skin service to 
	deploy the window style into the portal. Window styles can belong in with a window style category, this
	category and the window styles will need to be specified in resources file.
	</para>
        
        <para>The following gatein-resource.xml fragment will add MyThemeBlue and MyThemeRed to 
        the MyTheme category.</para>
        
        <programlisting role="XML">&lt;window-style&gt;
  &lt;style-name&gt;MyTheme&lt;/style-name&gt;
  &lt;style-theme&gt;
    &lt;theme-name&gt;MyThemeBlue&lt;/theme-name&gt;
  &lt;/style-theme&gt;
  &lt;style-theme&gt;
    &lt;theme-name&gt;MyThemeRed&lt;/theme-name&gt;
  &lt;/style-theme&gt;
&lt;/window-style&gt;</programlisting>

    <para>The windows style configuration for the default skin is configured in:</para>
    <filename>01eXoResources.war/WEB-INF/gatein-resources.xml</filename>

    <note><para>
    When a window style is defined in gatein-resources.xml file, it will be available
    to all portlets regardless if the current portal skin support the window decorator or 
    not. It is recommended that when a new window decorator is added that it is added 
    to all portal skins or that portal skins share a common stylesheet for window decorators.
    </para></note>

    </section>

	<section>
	<title>Window Style CSS</title>
	<para>
	In order for the skin service to display the window decorators, it must have CSS classes with specific
	naming in relation to the window style name. The service will try and display css based on this naming. 
	The css class must be included as part of the current portal skin for the window decorators to be displayed.
	</para>
	<para>The location of the window decorator css classes for the default portal theme is located at:</para>
	<filename>01eXoResources.war/skin/PortletThemes/Stylesheet.css</filename>
	
	<para></para>
        <para>Create the CSS file:</para>


    <programlisting>
/*---- MyTheme ----*/
.MyTheme .WindowBarCenter .WindowPortletInfo {
	margin-right: 80px; /* orientation=lt */
	margin-left: 80px; /* orientation=rt */
}

.MyTheme .WindowBarCenter .ControlIcon {
	float: right; /* orientation=lt */
	float: left; /* orientation=rt */
	width: 24px; 
	height: 17px;
	cursor: pointer;
	background-image: url('background/MyTheme.png');
}

.MyTheme .ArrowDownIcon {
	background-position: center 20px;
}

.MyTheme .OverArrowDownIcon {
	background-position: center 116px;
}

.MyTheme .MinimizedIcon {
	background-position: center 44px;
}

.MyTheme .OverMinimizedIcon {
	background-position: center 140px;
}

.MyTheme .MaximizedIcon {
	background-position: center 68px;
}

.MyTheme .OverMaximizedIcon {
	background-position: center 164px;
}

.MyTheme .RestoreIcon {
	background-position: center 92px;
}

.MyTheme .OverRestoreIcon {
	background-position: center 188px;
}

.MyTheme .NormalIcon {
	background-position: center 92px;
}

.MyTheme .OverNormalIcon {
	background-position: center 188px;
}

.MyTheme .Information {
	height: 18px; line-height: 18px;
	vertical-align: middle; font-size: 10px;
	padding-left: 5px; /* orientation=lt */
	padding-right: 5px; /* orientation=rt */
	margin-right: 18px; /* orientation=lt */
	margin-left: 18px; /* orientation=rt */
}

.MyTheme .WindowBarCenter .WindowPortletIcon {
	background-position: left top; /* orientation=lt */
	background-position: right top; /* orientation=rt */
	padding-left: 20px; /* orientation=lt */
	padding-right: 20px; /* orientation=rt */
	height: 16px;
	line-height: 16px;
}

.MyTheme .WindowBarCenter .PortletName {
	font-weight: bold;
	color: #333333;
	overflow: hidden;
	white-space: nowrap;
}

.MyTheme .WindowBarLeft {
	padding-left: 12px;
	background-image: url('background/MyTheme.png');
	background-repeat: no-repeat;
	background-position: left -148px;
}

.MyTheme .WindowBarRight {
	padding-right: 11px;
	background-image: url('background/MyTheme.png');
	background-repeat: no-repeat;
	background-position: right -119px;
}

.MyTheme .WindowBarCenter {
	background-image: url('background/MyTheme.png');
	background-repeat: repeat-x;
	background-position: left -90px;
	height: 21px;
	padding-top: 8px;
}

.MyTheme .MiddleDecoratorLeft {
	padding-left: 12px;
	background: url('background/MMyTheme.png') repeat-y left;
}

.MyTheme .MiddleDecoratorRight {
	padding-right: 11px;
	background: url('background/MMyTheme.png') repeat-y right;
}

.MyTheme .MiddleDecoratorCenter {
	background: #ffffff;
}

.MyTheme .BottomDecoratorLeft {
	padding-left: 12px;
	background-image: url('background/MyTheme.png');
	background-repeat: no-repeat;
	background-position: left -60px;
}

.MyTheme .BottomDecoratorRight {
	padding-right: 11px;
	background-image: url('background/MyTheme.png');
	background-repeat: no-repeat;
	background-position: right -30px;
}

.MyTheme .BottomDecoratorCenter {
	background-image: url('background/MyTheme.png');
	background-repeat: repeat-x;
	background-position: left top;
	height: 30px;
}
</programlisting>
</section>
<section>
<title>How to Set the Default Window Style</title>
To set the default window style to be used for a portal, you will to specify the css classes
for a theme called <literal>DefaultTheme</literal>.
<note><para>You do not need to specify the DefaultTheme in gatein-resources.xml</para></note>
</section>
  </section>
  
    <section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Portlet_Styles">
    <title>How to Create New Portlet skins</title>

    <para>Portlets often require additional styles that may not be defined by
    the portal skin. &PRODUCT; allows portlets to define additional
    stylesheets for each portlet and will append the corresponding
    <literal>link</literal> tags to the <literal>head</literal>.</para>

    <para>The link ID will be of the form
    <parameter>{portletAppName}{PortletName}</parameter>. For example:
    <literal>ContentPortlet</literal> in <literal>content.war</literal>, will
    give
    <parameter>id="content<literal>ContentPortlet"</literal></parameter></para>

    <para>To define a new CSS file to include whenever a portlet is available on a portal page, the
    following fragment needs to be added in gatein-resources.xml<programlisting>&lt;portlet-skin&gt;
  &lt;application-name&gt;portletAppName&lt;/application-name&gt;
  &lt;portlet-name&gt;PortletName&lt;/portlet-name&gt;
  &lt;skin-name&gt;Default&lt;/skin-name&gt;
  &lt;css-path&gt;/skin/DefaultStylesheet.css&lt;/css-path&gt;
&lt;/portlet-skin&gt;

&lt;portlet-skin&gt;
  &lt;application-name&gt;portletAppName&lt;/application-name&gt;
  &lt;portlet-name&gt;PortletName&lt;/portlet-name&gt;
  &lt;skin-name&gt;OtherSkin&lt;/skin-name&gt;
  &lt;css-path&gt;/skin/OtherSkinStylesheet.css&lt;/css-path&gt;
&lt;/portlet-skin&gt;</programlisting></para>

    <para>This will load the DefaultStylesheet.css when the Default skin is used and the
    OtherSkinStylesheet.css when the OtherSkin is used.</para>
    <note><para>If the current portal skin is not defined as part of the supported
    skins, then the portlet css class will not be loaded. It is recommended to update
    portlet skins whenever a new portal skin is created.</para></note>
    
    <section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Tips_and_Tricks-Change_portlet_icons">
      <title>Change portlet icons</title>

      <para>Each portlet can be represented by an unique icon that you can see in the
      portlet registry or page editor. This icon can be changed by adding an image to the
      directory of the portlet webapplication:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><filename>skin/DefaultSkin/portletIcons/<replaceable>icon_name.png</replaceable></filename>.</para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>

         <para>To be used correctly the icon must be named after the
          portlet.</para>
      <para>For example, the icon for an account portlet named AccountPortlet
      would be located at:</para>

      <itemizedlist>
        <listitem>
          <para><filename>skin/DefaultSkin/portletIcons/AccountPortlet.png</filename></para>
        </listitem>
      </itemizedlist>
      <note>
      <para>
      You must use <literal>skin/DefaultSkin/portletIcons/</literal> for the directory to store the
      portlet icon regardless of what skin is going to be used.
      </para>
      </note>
    </section>
  </section>
      <section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Portlet_Specification_CSS_Classes">
    <title>How to create a new Portlet Specification CSS Classes</title>
    <para>The portlet specification defines a set of default css classes that should be available for portlets.
    These classes are included as part of the portal skin. Please see the portlet specification for a list of the 
    default classes that should be available.</para>
    <para>For the default portal skin, the portlet specification CSS classes are defined in :</para>
    <filename>eXoResources.war/skin/Portlet/Stylesheet.css</filename>
    </section>
</section>
  
  
    <section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Skin_Configuration-Tips_and_Tricks">
    <title>Tips and Tricks</title>

    <section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Tips_and_Tricks-Easier_css_debuggin">
      <title>Easier css debugging</title>

      <para>By default, CSS files are cached and their imports are merged into
      a single CSS file at the server side. This reduces the number of HTTP
      requests from the browser to the server.</para>

      <para>The optimization code is quite simple as all the CSS files are
      parsed at the server startup time and all the @import and url(...)
      references are rewritten to support a single flat file. The result is
      stored in a cache directly used from the
      <literal>ResourceRequestFilter</literal>.</para>

      <para>Although the optimization is useful for a production environments,
      it may be easier to deactivate this optimization while debugging
      stylesheets. To do so, set the java system property
      <literal>exo.product.developing</literal> to
      <literal>true</literal>.</para>

      <para>For example, the property can be passed as a JVM parameter with
      <literal>-D</literal> option when running GateIn.</para>
      <programlisting>sh $JBOSS_HOME/bin/run.sh -Dexo.product.developing=true</programlisting>

      <orderedlist numeration="arabic">
        <listitem>
          <para>warning("This option may cause display bugs with certain
          browsers like Internet Explorer")</para>
        </listitem>
      </orderedlist>
    </section>
      <section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Tips_and_Tricks-Some_CSS_techniques">
      <title>Some CSS techniques</title>

      <para>It is recommended that users have some experience with CSS before
      studying &PRODUCT; CSS.</para>

      <para>&PRODUCT; relies heavily on CSS to create the layout and effects
      for the UI. Some common techniques for customizing &PRODUCT; CSS are
      explained below.</para>

      <section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Some_CSS_techniques-Decorator_pattern">
        <title>Decorator pattern</title>

        <para>The decorator is a pattern to create a contour or a curve around
        an area. In order to achieve this effect you need to create 9 cells.
        The BODY is the central area that you want to decorate. The other 8
        cells are distributed around the BODY cell. You can use the width,
        height and background image properties to achieve any decoration
        effect that you want.</para>
 
        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/PortalDevelopment/Skinning/decoratorPattern.png" format="PNG"
                     width="418" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <programlisting role="HTML">
&lt;div class="Parent"&gt;
  &lt;div class="TopLeft"&gt;
    &lt;div class="TopRight"&gt;
      &lt;div class="TopCenter"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="CenterLeft"&gt;
    &lt;div class="CenterRight"&gt;
      &lt;div class="CenterCenter"&gt;BODY&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div class="BottomLeft"&gt;
    &lt;div class="BottomRight"&gt;
      &lt;div class="BottomCenter"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
    &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</programlisting>
      </section>

      <section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Some_CSS_techniques-Left_margin_left_pattern">
        <title>Left margin left pattern</title>

        <para>Left margin left pattern is a technique to create 2 blocks side
        by side. The left block will have a fixed size and the right block
        will take the rest of the available space. When the user resizes the
        browser the added or removed space will be taken from the right
        block.</para>

        <mediaobject>
          <imageobject>
            <imagedata fileref="images/PortalDevelopment/Skinning/leftMarginPattern.png" format="PNG"
                     width="303" />
          </imageobject>
        </mediaobject>

        <programlisting role="HTML">
&lt;div class="Parent"&gt;
  &lt;div style="float: left; width: 100px"&gt;
  &lt;/div&gt;
  &lt;div style="margin-left: 105px;"&gt;
  &lt;div&gt;
  &lt;div style="clear: left"&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</programlisting>
      </section>
    </section>
  </section>
</section>
