<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../../User_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<section id="sect-User_Guide-Manage_Gadgets">
	<title>Manage Gadgets</title>
		<para>
			Gadgets are a small convenient applications that help portal users perform private actions. &PRODUCT; provides you with some gadgets by default (see <xref linkend="sect-User_Guide-Dashboard_Portlet-Using_the_Dashboard_Workspace"/>. 
		</para>
		<para>
			In addition to these ready-to-use gadgets, &PRODUCT; allows you to easily add gadgets organized in categories to meet your needs.
		</para>

	<section id="sect-User_Guide-Manage_Gadgets_in_User_Workspace-Manage_Gadget_Categories">
		<title>Manage Gadget Categories</title>
			<formalpara>
				<title>Add a Category</title>
				<para></para>
			</formalpara>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>
						Open the User Workspace on your left pane.
					</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>
						Click the tool icon to add a new category
					</para>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/UserWorkspace.png" format="PNG" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>
						The <emphasis role="bold">Gadget Containers Management</emphasis> dialog appears:
					</para>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/GadgetManagement.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</step>		
				<step>
					<para>
						Click the add icon to show the <emphasis role="bold">Gadget Container Form</emphasis> .
					</para>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/GadgetContainer.png" format="PNG" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
					<variablelist>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>Label</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>
								The display name of the category. This field is required and must have at least 3 characters.
								</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>Description</term>
							<listitem>
							<para>
								The brief description of the category. A length from 0 to 255 characters is allowed. This field is not required.
							</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
					</variablelist>
				</step>		
				<step>
					<para>
						Enter values for fields in the <emphasis role="bold">Gadget Container Form</emphasis> .
					</para>
				</step>		
				<step>
					<para>
						Click on the <emphasis role="bold">Save</emphasis> button to accept the new category or click <emphasis role="bold">Cancel</emphasis> to quit. After you added the new category you will see it in the dialog :
					</para>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/GadgetManagement1.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>	
				</step>
			</procedure>
		<formalpara>
			<title>Edit Categories</title>
				<para>
					Edit the information of an existing category by selecting it from the left pane, the selected category is marked by a symbol. Then click the edit icon to show the edit form. Change the current category information and click on the <emphasis role="bold">button</emphasis> to accept changes.
				</para>	
		</formalpara>

		<formalpara>
			<title>Deleting a Category</title>
				<para>
					Delete an existing category by selecting it from the left pane. In the message box Click on the <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis> button to confirm the deletion or click the <emphasis role="bold">Cancel</emphasis> button.
				</para>
		</formalpara>
		<para>
			Click on the <emphasis role="bold">Save</emphasis> button in the <emphasis role="bold">Gadget Containers Management</emphasis> dialog to accept or on the <emphasis role="bold">Cancel</emphasis> button to quit. Added categories will be displayed in list in the User Workspace.
		</para>
	</section>		
	<section id="sect-User_Guide-Manage_Gadgets_in_User_Workspace-Add_Gadgets">
		<title>Add Gadgets</title>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>
						Click the list icon to see category list and select the one you want to add a gadget to.
					</para>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/UserWorkspace1.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>
						Click the add icon at the bottom of the User Workspace to open the <emphasis role="bold">Add Application</emphasis> dialog:
					</para>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/AddApplication.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>
						Select a gadget by clicking the add icon (located next to the the gadget). The selected gadget is displayed immediately in the user workspace. Normally, you can see only two gadgets in the User Workspace. When there are more gadgets, some gadgets are not visible.
					</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>
						Click the scroll down icon or the scroll up icon at the bottom of the User Workspace to see the other gadgets. The scroll icons will be greyed out when you reach the end of the available gadgets.
					</para>
				</step>
		</procedure>	
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-User_Guide-Manage_Gadgets_in_User_Workspace-Edit_a_Gadget">
		<title>Edit a Gadget</title>
		<para>
			To edit a gadget, click the edit icon.
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-User_Guide-Manage_Gadgets_in_User_Workspace-Remove_a_Gadget">
		<title>Remove a Gadget</title>
		<para>
			Remove a gadget from the User Workspace by using the functional bar at the upper right corner of that gadget.
		</para>
		<para>
			Click the remove icon. When the confirmation message appears, click the <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis> button to accept or the <emphasis role="bold">Cancel</emphasis> to quit.
		</para>
	</section>

</section>
