<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../../User_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<section id="sect-User_Guide-Permissions">
	<title>Permissions</title>
	<para>
		Permission settings control what users can and cannot do within the portal and are set by portal administrators.
	</para>
	<para>
		Permission <emphasis role="bold">types</emphasis> dictate what a user can do within the portal. Two permission types are available as follows:
	</para>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><emphasis role="bold">Access</emphasis></term>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						This permission type allows users to utilize portal content, that is; sign in, rearrange portlets, etc. This permission can be set for multiple member groups.
					</para>
				</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><emphasis role="bold">Edit</emphasis></term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					This permission type allows users to change portal content. This includes actions such as changing page information, deleting pages etc. The <emphasis>edit</emphasis> permission is set for only one group at a time.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<para>
		Permission <emphasis role="bold"> levels</emphasis> dictate <emphasis>where</emphasis> in the portal the user's permission type applies. There are three permission levels:
	</para>

	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><emphasis role="bold">Portal</emphasis></term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The portal permission level includes all pages within the portal. Therefore, a user with the <emphasis role="bold">access</emphasis> permission type can view (but not edit) all the pages within the portal. A user with <emphasis role="bold">edit</emphasis> permission at the portal level, can change any page in the portal.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><emphasis role="bold">Page</emphasis></term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The page permission level restricts the user to particular pages. Users are only able to see and/or edit (depending on their permission <emphasis role="bold">type</emphasis>) pages they have been given access to.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term><emphasis role="bold">Portlet</emphasis></term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The portlet permission level allows users to create a page by dragging and dropping portlets into a page. Some portlets are only used for administrators while some are used for individuals thus administrators have to set the appropriate access permissions.
				</para>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>

	<para>
		Permission <emphasis role="bold">types</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">levels</emphasis> can be used to effectively control who can do what within the portal. For more information on setting permissions refer to <xref linkend="sect-User_Guide-Manage_Permissions"/>
	</para>
</section>


