<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../../User_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<section id="sect-User_Guide-Navigation">
	<title>Navigation</title>
	<para>
		Portal navigations are menus that contain hyperlinks to other parts of a Portal. They can help users to visualize the structure of a site. The default navigation menus in &PRODUCT; are located in the Toolbar (<xref linkend="sect-User_Guide-Toolbar-Concept"/>).
	</para>
	<para>
		There are three navigation types.
	</para>
	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
		<term>Site</term>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				This navigation links to separate sites of the parent Portal. Each site has only one navigation and it is automatically generated when the site is created.
			</para>
			<para>
				This functionality allows different sites to administer some Portal aspects (such as portlets) individually while maintaining other content standardized with the parent Portal.
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Group</term>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				The content of this navigation differs depending on the type of account logged in. 
			</para>
			<itemizedlist>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						If a user account in in effect, this navigation holds personal links set up by that user.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						When using a management account, this navigation contains links to pages for registered users as well as administrative tasks and personal links.
					</para>
				</listitem>
				<listitem>
					<para>
						In an administrator account the navigation adds further management abilities such as Internationalization and community management.
					</para>
				</listitem>
			</itemizedlist>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Dashboard</term>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				Each user has own navigation 'Dashboard' that contains links and portlets (or gadgets) that the user has selected. A user's navigation is created automatically when user is registered. This navigation only can be deleted when the user is deleted.
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	<para>
		When logged in as an Administrator, a fourth navigation appears in the Toolbar:
	</para>
	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
		<term>Site/Group Editor</term>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				This navigation appears as either <emphasis role="bold">Site Editor</emphasis> or <emphasis role="bold">Group Editor</emphasis> depending on the administrator's location within the portal.
			</para>
			<para>
				When in areas of the portal displaying content, the navigation shows as  <emphasis role="bold">Site Editor</emphasis> and in areas of the portal pertaining to users, the navigation shows as  <emphasis role="bold">Group Editor</emphasis>. 
			</para>
			<para>
				This navigation contains links to add a new pages to the portal, to edit a page or to change the portal's layout. Administrators can use these links to manage the portal.
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
</section>


