<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../../Reference_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Dynamic_Layouts">
	<title>Dynamic Layouts</title>
	<section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Dynamic_Layouts-Overview">
		<title>Overview</title>
		<para>
			The traditional way of rendering a portal page is a static one where you need a template, usually a jsp page, for each layout (2 columns, 3 columns and so on). That makes you depend on the integrator or developers as for each new layout you will need to ask for a custom development.
		</para>
		<para>
			GateIn has a dynamic way which creates a tree of nested UI containers that contain portlets as shown in the picture below. Each container is responsible for rendering its children. In the picture, the main container renders its children in several rows while the nested container displays them as columns.
		</para>
		<para>
			Furthermore, by manipulating the tree using the WYSIWYG editor, it allows you to create new containers, define how they will render their children, add new portlets.
		</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/portal.gif" format="GIF" />
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Dynamic_Layouts-Advanced_Drag_and_Drop_mechanism">
		<title>Advanced Drag and Drop mechanism</title>
		<para>
			As most portal use the static layout mechanism, they can only drag portlets from one static location, let's say a column, to another one.
		</para>
		<para>
			With GateIn Portal, it is possible to also drag the UI containers and the portlets and drop them in containers that are deeper or upper in the Portal component tree. This feature is unique and not just a tool!
		</para>
		<mediaobject>
			<imageobject>
				<imagedata fileref="images/image3.jpg" format="JPG" width="444" />
			</imageobject>
		</mediaobject>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-Reference_Guide-Dynamic_Layouts-Summary">
		<title>Summary</title>
		<para>
			With this innovative concept of dynamic layout, you can easily create portal pages with complex layout.
		</para>
	</section>

</section>


