<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../../User_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<section id="sect-User_Guide-FCK_Portlet">
	<title>FCK Portlet</title>
	<para>
		&PRODUCT; provides users with a portlet for the FCK Editor; a <ulink type="http" url="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/WYSIWYG">WYSIWYG</ulink> text editor that can be embedded in HTML web pages. FCK Editor offers users many of the commonly used word-processor functions such as writing, formatting text, creating tables, inserting links or pictures and more.
	</para>
	<mediaobject>
		<imageobject>
			<imagedata fileref="images/FCK1.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
		</imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
	<para>
		The main elements of the FCK portlet are:
	</para>
	<variablelist>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Toolbar</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					The area at the top of the editor which, like a desktop word-processsor, contains buttons used to perform various functions.
				</para>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/ToolBar1.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Editing Area</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					This is the main pane of the text editor portlet. It is where you type, view and format your text.
				</para>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/EditingArea1.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Context menu</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					A context menu is the program-specific right-click menu. It allows users to perform functions based on the context of where they clicked in the application. In the FCK Editor, context options include items like 'cut', 'copy' and 'paste'.
				</para>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/ContextMenu1.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
		<varlistentry>
			<term>Dialogues</term>
			<listitem>
				<para>
					In the FCK Editor, as in most programs, small windows called 'dialogues' may appear when some of the functions are activated. They provide the necessary information to accomplish those functions. 
				</para>
				<para>
					For an example: To insert a link into your document, you click the <emphasis role="bold">Link</emphasis> icon in the Toolbar. This will open a dialogue to allow you to input necessary information about the link.
				</para>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/Link.png" format="PNG" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
			</listitem>
		</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
</section>


