<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
]>
<section id="sect-User_Guide-Navigation">
	<!--         

    Copyright (C) 2009 eXo Platform SAS.
    
    This is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
    under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as
    published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2.1 of
    the License, or (at your option) any later version.
    
    This software is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
    but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
    MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
    Lesser General Public License for more details.
    
    You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
    License along with this software; if not, write to the Free
    Software Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA
    02110-1301 USA, or see the FSF site: http://www.fsf.org.

         --><title>Navigation</title>
	<para>
		Portal navigations are menus that list hyperlinks to other parts of a Portal. They can help users to visualize the structure of a site. The navigation menus in EPP 5.0 are located in a bar across the top of the 'Home' page.
	</para>
	<para>
		There are three navigation types.
	</para>
	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
		<term>Site</term>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				This navigation links to separate sites of the main Portal. Each site has only one navigation and it is automatically created when the site is created. This functionality allows different sites to administer some Portal aspects individually, such as portlets, while maintaining other content standardized with the parent Portal.
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Group</term>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				The content of this navigation differs depending on the type of account logged in. For user accounts the Groups navigation holds personal links set up by the user. For management accounts, it keeps the links to pages for registered Portal users as well as administrative tasks and personal links. In the administrator account, the navigation adds further management abilities such as Internationalization and community management.
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	<varlistentry>
		<term>Dashboard</term>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				Each user has own navigation 'Dashboard' that houses links and portlets (or gadgets) that the user has selected. A user's navigation is created automatically when user is registered. This navigation only can be deleted when the user is deleted.
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
	<para>
		When logged in as an Administrator, a fourth navigation appears in the Toolbar:
	</para>
	<variablelist>
	  <varlistentry>
		<term>Site Editor</term>
		<listitem>
			<para>
				This navigation contains links to add a new page to the portal, to edit a page or to change the portal's layout. Administrators can use these links to manage the portal.
			</para>
		</listitem>
	</varlistentry>
	</variablelist>
</section>


