<!--

    Copyright (C) 2009 eXo Platform SAS.
    
    This is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
    under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as
    published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2.1 of
    the License, or (at your option) any later version.
    
    This software is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
    but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
    MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
    Lesser General Public License for more details.
    
    You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
    License along with this software; if not, write to the Free
    Software Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA
    02110-1301 USA, or see the FSF site: http://www.fsf.org.

-->

<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook V4.4//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/sgml/4.4/docbookx.dtd">
<section>
	<title>Dynamic Layouts</title>
	<section>
		<title>Overview</title>
	</section>
	<para>Indeed, the usual way of rendering a portal page is a
		static one where you need a template, usually a jsp page, for each
		layout (2 columns, 3 columns and so on). That makes you depend on the
		integrator or developers as for each new layout you will need to ask
		for a custom development.</para>
	<para>GateIn, with its dynamic way that creates a tree of nested
		UI containers that contain portlets as shown in the picture below.
		Each container is responsible for rendering its children. In the
		picture, the main container renders its children in several rows while
		the nested container displays them as columns.</para>
	<para>Furthermore, by manipulating the tree using the
		WYSIWYG editor, it allows you to create new containers, define how
		they will render their children, add new portlets.</para>
	<mediaobject>
		<imageobject>
			<imagedata fileref="images/portal.gif" format="GIF"></imagedata>
		</imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
	<section>
		<title>Advanced Drag and Drop mechanism</title>
	</section>
	<para>As most portal use the static layout mechanism, they can only
		drag portlets from one static location, let's say a column, to another
		one.</para>
	<para>With GateIn Portal, it is possible to also drag the UI
		containers and the portlets and drop them in containers that are
		deeper or upper in the Portal component tree. This feature is unique
		and not just a tool!</para>
	<mediaobject>
		<imageobject>
			<imagedata fileref="images/image3.jpg" format="PNG"></imagedata>
		</imageobject>
	</mediaobject>
	<section>
		<title>Summary</title>
	</section>
	<para>With this innovative concept of dynamic layout, you can
		easily create portal pages with complex layout.</para>
</section>