<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../../User_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<section id="sect-User_Guide-Manage_Pages">
	<!--     

    Copyright (C) 2009 eXo Platform SAS.
    
    This is free software; you can redistribute it and/or modify it
    under the terms of the GNU Lesser General Public License as
    published by the Free Software Foundation; either version 2.1 of
    the License, or (at your option) any later version.
    
    This software is distributed in the hope that it will be useful,
    but WITHOUT ANY WARRANTY; without even the implied warranty of
    MERCHANTABILITY or FITNESS FOR A PARTICULAR PURPOSE. See the GNU
    Lesser General Public License for more details.
    
    You should have received a copy of the GNU Lesser General Public
    License along with this software; if not, write to the Free
    Software Foundation, Inc., 51 Franklin St, Fifth Floor, Boston, MA
    02110-1301 USA, or see the FSF site: http://www.fsf.org.

     --><title>Manage Pages</title>
<warning>
<para>
The <emphasis role="bold">Administration</emphasis> menu entry reported to be under the <emphasis role="bold">GateIn Start</emphasis> button does not exist in GateIn 3.0 Beta 3. Therefore some of the instructions in this section may be incomplete or inaccurate.
</para>
</warning>
		<para>
			&PRODUCT; users can quickly add, edit, delete and view pages effectively in a comprehensive list. Follow the guide below to manage portal pages:
		</para>

		<section id="sect-User_Guide-Manage_Pages-Add_a_new_Page_in_the_Page_List">
			<title>Add a new Page in the Page List</title>
				<para>
					You easily add a new page by following these simple steps:
				</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>
							Go to <emphasis role="bold">Site </emphasis> -&gt;<emphasis role="bold">Administration</emphasis> -&gt; <emphasis role="bold">Advanced</emphasis> --&gt; <emphasis role="bold">Manage Pages</emphasis>.
						</para>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/ManagePage.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Click on Add New Page
						</para>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="images/ManagePage2.6.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
						<variablelist>
							<varlistentry>
								<term>Add New Page</term>
									<listitem>
										<para>
											This button allows you to add a new page.
										</para>
									</listitem>
							</varlistentry>
							<varlistentry>
								<term>Back</term>
									<listitem>
										<para>
											This button returns you to home page.
										</para>
									</listitem>
								</varlistentry>
						</variablelist>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Click the <emphasis role="bold">Add New Page</emphasis> button.
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Enter values for fields in the <emphasis role="bold">Page Setting</emphasis> tab
						</para>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/PageSetting.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
					<variablelist>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>Page Id</term>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										A string that identifies the page. It is automatically generated when you finish creating the page.
									</para>
								</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>Owner type</term>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										If the page <emphasis role="bold">Owner type</emphasis> is <emphasis>portal</emphasis> the page is created for a portal. Therefore only users who have edit permissions on the portal level can create this page type. 
									</para>
									<para>
										The name of the current portal is automatically selected for <emphasis role="bold">Owner id</emphasis> ensuring the edit permissions are assigned to users who can edit the current portal.
									</para>
									<para>
										If the page <emphasis role="bold">Owner type</emphasis> is <emphasis>group</emphasis> the page  is created for a group. Therefore only users who have <emphasis>manager</emphasis> permissions for that group can create this page type.
									</para>
									<mediaobject>
										<imageobject>
											<imagedata fileref="images/PageSetting1.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
										</imageobject>
									</mediaobject>
								</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>Owner Id</term>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										The name of the page owner. When the owner type is set to <emphasis>group</emphasis>, a list of groups will allow you to select one user as the 'owner'.	
									</para>
								</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>Page Name</term>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										The name of the page. This is a required field and must be unique. Only alphabetical, numerical and underscore characters are allowed to be used for this field and the name must be at least 3 and no more than 30 characters in length.
									</para>
								</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>Page title</term>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										The title of the the page. This is an optional field. If you choose to add a title to the page it must be at least 3 and no more than 30 characters in length.
									</para>
								</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>Show Max Window</term>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										The option allows users to choose whether the page is shown at maximum size or not.
									</para>
								</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
					</variablelist>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Enter values for fields in the <emphasis role="bold">Permission Setting</emphasis> tab
						</para>
							<mediaobject>
								<imageobject>
									<imagedata fileref="images/PermissionSetting1.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
								</imageobject>
							</mediaobject>
						<variablelist>
						  <varlistentry>
							<term>Access Permission</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									The content of this tab is identical to the <emphasis role="bold">Owner type</emphasis> field in the <emphasis role="bold">Page Setting</emphasis> tab. Therefore, all users having access rights for the type selected in the <emphasis role="bold">Owner type</emphasis> field will appear in this tab. But users can also change the value of this tab.
								</para>
								<para>
								Check the check box if you want to share access with everyone or click the <emphasis role="bold">Add Permission</emphasis> button to assign permission on group level, then select a group and membership or click the trash can icon to remove a group from the list.
								</para>
								<mediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="images/EditPermission1.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
									</imageobject>
								</mediaobject>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>Edit Permission</term>
							<listitem>
								<para>
									The content of this tab depends on the value of the <emphasis role="bold">Owner type</emphasis> field in the <emphasis role="bold">Page Setting</emphasis> tab.
								</para>
								<para>
								If the <emphasis role="bold">Owner type</emphasis> is "group", edit permission is assigned to users who are "manager" of the group that is selected in <emphasis role="bold">Owner id</emphasis>. You can only change this value when editing the page.
								</para>
								<mediaobject>
									<imageobject>
										<imagedata fileref="images/EditPermission2.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
									</imageobject>
								</mediaobject> 
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						</variablelist>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Click the <emphasis role="bold">Save</emphasis> button to accept creating a new page or the <emphasis role="bold">Cancel</emphasis> button to quit the form.
						</para>
					</step>
			</procedure>
		</section>
	
		<section id="sect-User_Guide-Manage_Pages-Edit_a_Page">
			<title>Edit a Page</title>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>
							Go to <emphasis role="bold">GateIn Start</emphasis> -&gt; <emphasis role="bold">Administration</emphasis> -&gt; <emphasis role="bold">Advanced</emphasis> --&gt; <emphasis role="bold">Manage Pages</emphasis>
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Click the edit icon on the row of page you want to edit in the existing pages list.
						</para>
						<para>
							Click the edit icon to show a form to edit page properties.
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							The properties presented in the <emphasis role="bold">Page Properties</emphasis> window are the same as those outlined in <xref linkend="sect-User_Guide-Manage_Pages-Add_a_new_Page_in_the_Page_List"/>.
						</para>
						<variablelist>
							<varlistentry>
								<term>Permission Setting</term> 
								<listitem>
									<para>
										This form is supported for pages with <emphasis>group</emphasis> or <emphasis>portal</emphasis> ownershuip types. Because a user's page is private, no user, other than the creator, can access or edit it.
									</para>	
									<para>
										Permission on each page is set in two levels: <emphasis role="bold">Access right</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">Edit right</emphasis>.
									</para>
								</listitem>
							</varlistentry>
							<varlistentry>
								<term>Access right</term> 
								<listitem>
									<para>
										The page <emphasis role="bold">Access right</emphasis> can be set to specific user groups or set to everyone (this includes unregistered users). Current access permissions on page are listed and you can remove permissions (by clicking the delete icon) or add further permission (by click the <emphasis role="bold">Add Permission</emphasis> button). Populating the <emphasis role="bold">Make it public</emphasis> check box will allow all users (registered or unregistered) to access the page.
									</para>
								</listitem>
							</varlistentry>
							<varlistentry>
								<term>Edit right</term> 
								<listitem>
									<para>
										The <emphasis role="bold">Edit right</emphasis> allows users to change information on a page. <emphasis role="bold">Edit right</emphasis> only is set for a group of users. <emphasis role="bold">Edit right</emphasis> can be set for  one specific membership type within a particular group (<emphasis role="bold">*</emphasis> allows every membership type in a group). If you want to re-assign this right to another group, click <emphasis role="bold">Select Permission</emphasis> to choose another one.
									</para>
								</listitem>
							</varlistentry>
						</variablelist>
					</step>
					<step>
						<variablelist>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>Editing page container layout</term> 
								<listitem>
									<para>
										Click the Show Container icon to show current container layout of selected page on your right and all the container layouts list on the left pane.
									</para>
									<para>
										If you want to change the current layout, select a layout type from the list on the left pane, then drag the template you want into the right pane. The new container will be displayed on the right pane. You can change the position of the current container by dragging it to another place on the right pane or remove it completely by clicking the delete icon in the right corner.
									</para>
								</listitem>
							</varlistentry>
						</variablelist>
					</step>
					<step>
						<variablelist>
							<varlistentry>
								<term>Editing page portlet layout</term>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										Click the Show Portlet icon to show current portlet layout of page.
									</para>
									<para>
										If you want to change the current layout, select a layout type from the list on the left pane, then drag it into the right pane. The new portlet will be added and displayed in the right pane. You can change the position of the current portlet by dragging it to the place you want on the right pane, or remove it completely by clicking the delete icon.
									</para>
								</listitem>
							</varlistentry>
						</variablelist>
					</step>
				</procedure>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-User_Guide-Manage_Pages-View_a_Page">
		<title>View a Page</title>
		<para>
			View any page in the existing pages list by clicking on the <emphasis role="bold">View</emphasis> icon corresponding to the page you want to view.
		</para>
	</section>
	
	<section id="sect-User_Guide-Manage_Pages-Delete_a_Page">
		<title>Delete a Page</title>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>
						Go to <emphasis role="bold">GateIn Admin</emphasis> -&gt; <emphasis role="bold">Administration</emphasis> -&gt; <emphasis role="bold">Advanced</emphasis> --&gt; <emphasis role="bold">Manage Pages</emphasis>. You will be presented with a list of all existing pages.
					</para>
				</step>	
				<step>
					<para>
						Click the trash can icon in the row of the page you want to delete. It will display the confirmation message.
					</para>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/http.png" format="PNG" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>		
				</step>	
				<step>
					<para>
						Click the <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis> button to process the deletion or <emphasis role="bold">Cancel</emphasis> button to quit without deleting the page.
					</para>
				</step>
			</procedure>
	</section>

</section>


