<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8' ?>
<!DOCTYPE section PUBLIC "-//OASIS//DTD DocBook XML V4.5//EN" "http://www.oasis-open.org/docbook/xml/4.5/docbookx.dtd" [
<!ENTITY % BOOK_ENTITIES SYSTEM "../../User_Guide.ent">
%BOOK_ENTITIES;
]>
<section id="sect-User_Guide-User_management">
	<title>User management</title>
	<para>
		&PRODUCT; offers a number of tools to assist Administrators to manage a number of registered users, groups and memberships easily and effectively.
	</para>

	  <section id="sect-User_Guide-User_Management-Manage_users">
				<title>Manage users</title>
					<para>
						Select the <emphasis role="bold">Group</emphasis> navigation in the Toolbar. Under the <emphasis role="bold">Executive Board's Pages</emphasis> heading is a link to <emphasis role="bold">Organization</emphasis> options. 
					</para>
					<para>
						Clicking <emphasis>Users and Groups Management</emphasis> in this list will open an easily navigated table of current registered users. 
					</para>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/UserManage.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
					<para>
						Administrators can see all existing registered users and search, edit or even delete them. Each user's groups and memberships (roles) in these groups are also available. You can not add users to a group but you can remove them from the group.
					</para>
	</section>

	<section id="sect-User_Guide-User_Management-Search_a_user">
		<title>Search a user</title>
			<para>
				The Administrator can search for specific users by username, first name, last name or email address.
			</para>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>
							Select the parameter (name, email, etc) by which you would like to search from the drop-down menu.
						</para>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="images/SearchUser.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>					
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Type the search terms for the user that you want to locate. You may not need to enter the complete title as the tool will present partial match search results.
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Click the 'find' icon to begin the search.
						</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
	</section>

	<section id="sect-User_Guide-User_Management-Edit_a_user">
		<title>Edit a user</title>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					 <para>
						Locate the user you wish to edit.
					</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>
						Click the edit icon (next to the trash icon) in the list entry of that user.
					</para>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/Demo1.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>
						Select the <emphasis role="bold">Account Info</emphasis> tab to view and change the essential user information.
					</para>
					<variablelist>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>User Name</term>
							<listitem>
							<para>
								The <emphasis role="bold">User Name</emphasis> field cannot be changed. Other fields <emphasis role="bold">First Name</emphasis> , <emphasis role="bold">Last Name</emphasis> , <emphasis role="bold">Email Address</emphasis> can be changed.
							</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>Change Password</term>
							<listitem>
							<para>
								The <emphasis role="bold">Change Password</emphasis> option allows an administrator to set a new password for a user. When the <emphasis role="bold">Change Password</emphasis> option is unchecked, <emphasis role="bold">New Password</emphasis> and <emphasis role="bold">Confirm Password</emphasis> are hidden. Passwords must contain at least 6 characters and can contain letters, numbers and punctuation marks.
							</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
					</variablelist>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>
						Select the <emphasis role="bold">User Profile</emphasis> tab to view and change profile information. The <emphasis role="bold">Language</emphasis> field is used to set the display language for that user.
					</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>
						Select the <emphasis role="bold">User Membership</emphasis> tab to see a user's group membership information.
					</para>
					<mediaobject>
						<imageobject>
							<imagedata fileref="images/Demo3.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
						</imageobject>
					</mediaobject>
					<variablelist>
						<varlistentry>
							<term>User Membership</term>
							<listitem>
							<para>
								The <emphasis role="bold">User Membership</emphasis> tab indicates which group (or groups) the selected user belongs to. In the above figure, the user "demo" is a member of two groups: "guests" and "users". The parent group of both is "platform".
							</para>
							<para>
								To remove the user from a group, click the trash can icon on the row of the membership you want to revoke.
							</para>
							</listitem>
						</varlistentry>
					</variablelist>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>
						Click the <emphasis role="bold">Save</emphasis> button to submit changes.
					</para>
				</step>
			</procedure>
	</section>

	<section id="sect-User_Guide-User_Management-Delete_a_user">
		<title>Delete a user</title>
			<procedure>
				<step>
					<para>
						Locate the user you wish to delete in the <emphasis role="bold">User Management</emphasis> form.
					</para> 
					<para>
						Click the trash icon in the list entry corresponding to the user that you want to delete.
					</para>
				</step>
				<step>
					<para>
						Click the <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis> button in the confirmation message to confirm or the <emphasis role="bold">Cancel</emphasis> button to quit without changing anything.
					</para>
				</step>
			</procedure>
		</section>

		<section id="sect-User_Guide-User_Management-Manage_groups">
			<title>Manage groups</title>
				<para>
					Select the <emphasis role="bold">Group Management</emphasis> tab in the <emphasis role="bold">Organization</emphasis> form.
				</para>
				<para>
					By default, all existing groups will be displayed on the left pane. This tab is used to add new, edit or delete a group. The right pane shows information about the selected group including information about the members in the specific group and a small form to add a new user to a group.
				</para>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/GroupManage.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
		</section>

		<section id="sect-User_Guide-User_Management-Add_a_new_group">
			<title>Add a New Group</title>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>
							Choose the path to create a new group by selecting the groups from list on the left pane or clicking the arrow icon if you want to create a group in a higher level. The selected path is displayed in the path bar.
						</para>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject role="html">
								<imagedata fileref="images/Admin1.png" format="PNG" />
							</imageobject>
							<imageobject role="fo">
								<imagedata fileref="images/Admin1.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="50mm"/>
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Click the <emphasis role="bold">Add New Group</emphasis> icon. The <emphasis role="bold">Add New Group</emphasis> form will be displayed on the right pane:
						</para>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject role="html">
								<imagedata fileref="images/AddGroup.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
							</imageobject>
							<imageobject role="fo">
								<imagedata fileref="images/AddGroup.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="110mm"/>
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
						<variablelist>
							<varlistentry>
								<term><emphasis role="bold">Group Name</emphasis></term>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										The name of the new group. This field is required and any length from 3 to 30 characters is allowed. Once saved this name cannot be edited.
									</para>
									</listitem>
							</varlistentry>
							<varlistentry>
								<term><emphasis role="bold">Label</emphasis></term>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										The display name of the group. Any length from 3 to 30 characters is allowed.
									</para>
								</listitem>
							</varlistentry>
							<varlistentry>
								<term><emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis></term>
								<listitem>
									<para>
										A description of the group. Any length from 3 to 30 characters is allowed.
									</para>
								</listitem>
							</varlistentry>
						</variablelist>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Fill in the required fields. Only letters, numbers and underscore characters are allowed for the <emphasis role="bold">Group Name</emphasis> field. The name must be unique within the portal.
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							 Click the <emphasis role="bold">Save</emphasis> button to accept entered values or the <emphasis role="bold">Cancel</emphasis> button to quit.
						</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
		</section>

		<section id="sect-User_Guide-User_Management-Edit-a-group">
			<title>Edit a group</title>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>
							Select the path to the group you want to edit by selecting the groups from list on the left pane.
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Click the edit icon to show the <emphasis role="bold">Edit Group</emphasis> form for the selected group. This form is identical to the <emphasis role="bold">New Group</emphasis> form.
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Make the desired changes in the approapraite fields. You can not change the Group Name, however you may change to the <emphasis role="bold">Label</emphasis> field if you wish to refer to the group by a different name. You are also able to edit the <emphasis role="bold">Description</emphasis> field should it be appropriate. 
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Click the <emphasis role="bold">Save</emphasis> button to accept changes or the <emphasis role="bold">Cancel</emphasis> button to cancel changes and return to the <emphasis role="bold">Group Info</emphasis> form.
						</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
		</section>

		<section id="sect-User_Guide-User_Management-Add_a_new_user_to_a_group">
			<title>Add a new user to a group</title>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>
							Select the path to the group you want to edit by selecting the groups from the list on the left pane. The Group's information is displayed including the user list and a form which allows the addition of a new user.
						</para>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject>
								<imagedata fileref="images/AddMember1.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Enter the username of the new user of the selected group.
						</para>
						<para>
							If you are unsure of the exact username of the user you wish to add to the group, you can use the search function to locate them. 
						</para>
						<para>
							Refer to <xref linkend="sect-User_Guide-User_Management-Search_a_user" /> for instructions on how to locate a user.
						</para>
						<para>
							After you have found the required username, click the <emphasis role="bold">Add</emphasis> button and the complete username will populate the <emphasis role="bold">Add member</emphasis> form.
							</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Select the membership for the user in a group from memberships list. The refresh icon can be used to update the memberships list if there are any changes to incorporate.
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Click the <emphasis role="bold">Save</emphasis> button to accept adding the selected user to a specific group with the selected membership type.
						</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
		</section>

		<section id="sect-User_Guide-User_Management-Edit_the_user_membership_in_a_group">
			<title>Edit the user membership in a group</title>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>
							Click the edit icon corresponding to a specific user with a membership in the <emphasis role="bold">Group Info</emphasis> table to open the <emphasis role="bold">Edit Membership</emphasis> form :
						</para>
						<mediaobject>
							<imageobject role="html">
								<imagedata fileref="images/EditMember1.png" format="PNG" />
							</imageobject>
							<imageobject role="fo">
								<imagedata fileref="images/EditMember1.png" format="PNG" contentwidth="90mm"/>
							</imageobject>
						</mediaobject>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Change the membership of the selected user by selecting another value in the <emphasis role="bold">Membership</emphasis> field.
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Complete editing the selected user by clicking the <emphasis role="bold">Save</emphasis> button.
						</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
		</section>

		<section id="sect-User_Guide-User_Management-Delete_a_group">
			<title>Delete a group</title>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>
							Select the path to the group you want to delete by selecting the groups from list on the left pane.
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Click the trash icon to delete the group.
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Click the <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis> button on the confirmation message to accept or the <emphasis role="bold">Cancel</emphasis> button to quit without deleting.
						</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
		</section>

		<section id="sect-User_Guide-User_Management-Manage_memberships">
			<title>Manage memberships</title>
				<para>
					The roles of an user in the specific group are managed in the <emphasis role="bold">Membership Management</emphasis> form.
				</para>
				<para>
					Currently there are three membership types: <emphasis>Manager</emphasis>, <emphasis>Member</emphasis> and <emphasis>Validator</emphasis>. By default, Manager has the highest rights in a group. 
				</para>
				<para>
					Administrators can add new, edit or delete a membership type. Select the <emphasis role="bold">Membership Management</emphasis> tab in the <emphasis role="bold">Organization</emphasis> portlet.
				</para>
				<para>
					This will open a membership type list and a form to add new/edit:
				</para>
				<mediaobject>
					<imageobject>
						<imagedata fileref="images/MembershipManage1.png" format="PNG" width="444" />
					</imageobject>
				</mediaobject>
		</section>

		<section id="sect-User_Guide-User_Management-Add_a_new_membership_type">
			<title>Add a new membership type</title>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>
							In the <emphasis role="bold">Add/Edit Membership</emphasis> form, enter the values for the membership name field (required) and the description field (optional). Only letters, digits, dots, dashes and underscores are allowed for the membership name.
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Click the <emphasis role="bold">Save</emphasis> button to accept adding the new membership or click <emphasis role="bold">Reset</emphasis> button to clear the entered values.
						</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
		</section>

		<section id="sect-User_Guide-User_Management-Edit_a_membership_type">
			<title>Edit a membership type</title>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>
							Click the edit icon in the row of the membership type you want to edit. The selected Membership type information is displayed in the Add/Edit Membership form.
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Make the desired changes in this form.
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Click <emphasis role="bold">Save</emphasis> to accept changes.
						</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
		</section>

		<section id="sect-User_Guide-User_Management-Delete_a_membership_type">
			<title>Delete a membership type</title>
				<procedure>
					<step>
						<para>
							Click the trash icon in the row of the membership type that you want to delete.
						</para>
					</step>
					<step>
						<para>
							Click the <emphasis role="bold">OK</emphasis> button in the confirmation message to accept the deletion.
						</para>
					</step>
				</procedure>
		</section>
</section>
